Finding Aid for Patricia Clancy Montgomery Papers, 1973-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Patricia Clancy Montgomery Papers 1973-2004
Montgomery, Patricia Clancy, 1934-
0636 Aa 2
Educator, founder of Clonlara School in Ann Arbor, speaker and activist on behalf of home schooling and alternative methods of education. The collection includes files relating to Clonlara School and to the Clonlara Home Based Education Program, as well as to Montgomery’s work with various organizations, including the National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools and the National Homeschool Association.
12 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Patricia Montgomery (donor no. 9707 ) in 2006 in two separate accessions.
The collection is open to research.
Patricia Montgomery was born October 13, 1934 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. A life-long teacher, she began her teaching career as a nun with the Sisters of Divine Providence in various schools in Pennsylvania, Ohio, and Michigan (1953-1961). She received her Bachelor of Education from Duquesne in 1961, then went on to teach in Westland and Ann Arbor, Michigan. She received her Master of Arts in Education in 1967 from the University of Michigan. At this time, she determined to establish an elementary school to be an alternative to the public school system. Her school, she believed, would encourage humane and non-structured education. The result was the founding and establishment of Clonlara School, a "free school" based on the Summerhill school of A. S. Neill. Beginning first as pre-school, Clonlara soon became a full elementary school, and then later a high school.
The success of Clonlara and the encouragement that she received led Montgomery to develop the Clonlara Home Based Education Program that other like-minded individuals could incorporate into their own community or home schooling efforts. The need for a network for those engaged in the alternative schooling movement also spurred Montgomery and others to establish the National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools.
Publicity about Clonlara drew attention from journalists and teachers both nationally (e.g. appearances on the Donahue program) and internationally (the visit of a Japanese television news crew to Ann Arbor). Montgomery was called upon for numerous speaking engagements and television appearances; she wrote frequently on topics of home-schooling and non-traditional educational methods; and she corresponded with educators, students, and others who shared her philosophy.
The Patricia Clancy Montgomery papers include files relating to Clonlara School and to the Clonlara Home Based Education Program, as well as to Montgomery’s work with various organizations, including the National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools and the National Homeschool Association. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical, Writings, and Personal; Clonlara School; Clonlara School Outreach to Japan; Clonlara School Litigation; Legislation; People file; Organization file; National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools; Home Schooling Background Material; Clonlara School Home Based Education Program; The Learning Edge newsletter; Videocassettes; and Audiocassettes.
Subjects:
Montgomery, Patricia Clancy, 1934-; Alternative schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Clonlara Home Based Education Program.; Clonlara School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Home schooling--United States.; Educators--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Education--Japan.; National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools (U.S.); National Homeschool Association.; Educational law and legislation--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Montgomery, Patricia Clancy, 1934-; Alternative schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Schools.; Clonlara School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); School children--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Montgomery, Patricia Clancy, 1934-; Clonlara Home Based Education Program.; Clonlara School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Home schooling--United States.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical, Writings, and Personal
  The Biographical, Writings and Personal series contains a variety of documents pertaining to the life and career of Patricia Montgomery. There is a wealth of articles and press materials relating to Montgomery and the Clonlara School, including several documents written by Montgomery herself. These materials span from the 1970s through to the early 1990s. Of special interest are the various interviews with Montgomery, including a transcript from a 1981 appearance on the Phil Donahue show. The series also contains a variety of background biographical information, and personal correspondence with friends and colleagues, as well as two folders containing letters to and from Patricia Montgomery's daughter Chandra and son Chai. Of further note, are the six folders chronicling her work as a mentor to students at Columbia Pacific University.
  - Vita and related (Box 1)
  - Published interview with PM in Home Education, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Dissertation, Wayne State University, entitled "Toward Freedom in Education: A Survey of Independent Alternative Schools" 1980 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlet: "The High School Student in a Home School" 1986 (Box 1)
  - Article written with Jose Santiago: "The Computer Goes to School -- An Early Start" 1973 (Box 1)
  - Article: "Home Education in the United States, An Overview" (Box 1)
  - Article: "A Basic Ingredient of Alternative Education: A Blend of Philosophies" (Box 1)
  - Invitations for Pat Montgomery to speak 1971-1978 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous articles by or about PM and Clonlara (Box 1)
  - Television appearance on the Donohue Show; also reactions to speeches given (Box 1)
    (include transcript of Phil Donohue interview)
  - Pat Montgomery: notes, outlines, and writing drafts (Box 1)
  - Personal letters 1969-1996 (Box 1)
  - Personal letters 1997-2005 (Box 1)
  - Letters exchanged with daughter Chandra Montgomery (Box 1)
  - Letters exchanged with daughter Chai Montgomery (Box 1)
  - Columbia Pacific University, 6 folders (Box 1)
    (PM was mentor to students writing on topics of education)
- Clonlara School
  Administrative materials make up the bulk of the Clonlara School series. Such documents include articles of incorporation filed with the State of Michigan, financial materials of the organization, meeting notes of the management council, information relating to school curriculum, statistical documents from the 1970s into the 2000s, and a variety of other planning records. The series also consists of Clonlara program and teacher training materials, and documents relating to national and international affiliated schools. Public relations pamphlets and other publications are also featured.
  - Affiliate (or satellite) schools (Box 1)
  - Articles on Clonlara history (Box 1)
  - Articles of incorporation/by-laws (Box 1)
  - Articles of incorporation (Box 1)
    (filing with the State Board of Education)
  - Bay Foundation grant proposal 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Buildings and expansion (Box 1)
  - Capital campaign (Box 1)
  - Clonlara conference materials and evaluations 1995-2003 (Box 1)
  - Clonlara international affiliates (including Korea, Sweden, and Bermuda) (Box 1)
  - Clonlara Spain (Box 1)
  - Clonlara West, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Clonlara publications and brochures, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - CompuHigh curriculum (Box 2)
  - Enrollment and data analysis 1974-2003 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Education Grant Proposal 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Field trip 1972 (Box 2)
    (mainly photographic snapshots)
  - Finances 1970-2000 (Box 2)
  - Individualized Curriculum and secondary academics curriculum (Box 2)
  - Mailings and announcements (Box 2)
  - Management Council (Box 2)
  - Meetings and minutes (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Grant Proposal 1996 (Box 2)
  - Organization transition 2004 (Box 2)
  - Planning/fund-raising file (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Portable classroom fire 1976 (Box 2)
  - Questionnaire sent out to former parents of students and to former students 1993 (Box 2)
  - Research study 1975 (Box 2)
  - State regulations and Clonlara guidelines 1994-1999 (Box 2)
  - Summer Program proposals and information 1970-1982 (Box 2)
  - Teacher orientation materials 1977, 1979, 1998 and unknown dates (Box 2)
- Clonlara School Outreach to Japan
  The Clonlara School Outreach to Japan series documents Patricia Montgomery's visits to Japan and reception of Japanese delegates to Ann Arbor in 1982 and 1983, as well as the termination of the partnership between Clonlara and one Japanese school in 2000. Correspondence between Montgomery and Japanese teachers and students are included in the series.
  - Visit of PM to Japanese schools and educators July-August 1982 (Box 3)
  - Visit of Japanese television documentary producers to Clonlara 1982 (Box 3)
  - Visit of Japanese teachers to Clonlara 1983 (Box 3)
    (includes subsequent correspondence with these and other teachers and educators)
  - Draft and background material for book on Japanese education written with Claire Korn entitled "Free Schools, Reality and Dream" (Box 3)
  - Kaze-no-Gakuen partnership and termination June 8, 2000-July 6, 2000 (Box 3)
  - 8th International Democratic Education Conference in Japan July 2000 (Box 3)
- Clonlara School Litigation
  The Clonlara School Litigation series is composed of legal documents regarding a number of civil actions brought by Clonlara Inc. and associated individuals against local and state level education officials over the way in which the State Board of Education dealt with the issue of home schooling. Included are the depositions made by Montgomery and the correspondence she had with her attorney.
  - Clonlara, Inc., John and Sandra Bennett, Leonard and Julia Kuhar v. Michigan State Board of Education et al AND Clonlara, Inc. Robert Gibson and Cynthia Gibson and Deborah McConnell v. Michigan State Board of Education et al. (Box 4)
    - Deposition of Patricia Montgomery 1988, 9 volumes (Box 4)
    - Testimony and briefs (Box 4)
    - Working files for the cases, 0.4 linear feet (Box 4)
    - Working files for the cases (Box 5)
      contents not listed
    - Working files for the cases, 0.5 linear feet (Box 6)
    - Correspondence regarding litigation, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Legislation
  Bills affecting the nature and status of alternative and home schools can be found in the Legislation series of the collection. These legislative materials date from about 1994-1996. Also included are responses from both Clonlara and other homeschooling organizations, as well as correspondence with lawmakers, media materials and other publications regarding the proposed laws.
  - H.R.6 1994
    (proposed amendment to require teacher certification in subject area)
    - Ad Hoc Coalition of National Homeschooling Organizations (Box 6)
    - Clonlara response (Box 6)
    - Communications on the floor (Box 6)
    - Correspondence with politicians (Box 6)
    - Pat Farenga (Box 6)
    - Home School Legal Defense Association (HSLDA) (Box 6)
    - Group endorsement of Kildee Amendment (Box 6)
    - Larry Kaseman (Box 6)
    - Media (Box 6)
    - Publications (Box 6)
    - Victory brochure (Box 6)
  - S.B.679 1996 (Box 6)
    (removes home schools from nonpublic school status, meaning they no longer qualify for services provided to nonpublic schools)
  - Clonlara response (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with legislators (Box 6)
  - Home School Legal Defense Association (HSLDA) (Box 6)
  - Michigan Legislation H.B.4521 and 5803 (Box 6)
  - Parental Rights and Responsibilities Act 1996 (Box 6)
- People file
  The People File series is a collection of correspondence and other documents pertaining to Montgomery's colleagues in the local, statewide, and national alternative schools movement. The series is ordered alphabetically by the individual's last name, and in a large number of instances, the organization the person is affiliated with is noted parenthetically in the finding aid list. For more information, and related materials, the researcher should consult The National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools.
  - Amabile, Carmen (Box 7)
    (promotion materials)
  - Antonetti, Pia 1985-1990 (Box 7)
  - Baldwin, Bob 1993 (Box 7)
  - Barker, Penny 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Baseman, Diana 1990, 1995 (Box 7)
    (Pennsylvania Home Education News)
  - Becknell, Clyde and Matt 1984 (Box 7)
  - Berggren, Kurt 1994-1995 (Box 7)
    (Ann Arbor attorney)
  - Bethel, Dayle 1991 (Box 7)
    (Osaka Learning Center, Japan)
  - Boswell, Jane 1995 (Box 7)
    (Home education & Family Services, Gray, Maine)
  - Bricker, Paul 1993 (Box 7)
  - Burkart, Gene J 1990 (Box 7)
  - Chludzinski, George and Anne Marie 1983 (Box 7)
  - Clement, Allison 1988 (Box 7)
  - Crafts, Ralph 1982-1985 (Box 7)
  - Crawford, Lisle and Ruth 1983 (Box 7)
  - Creech, Kathleen 1989-1991 (Box 7)
    (Goat Hill Academy)
  - Decker, Nancy 1980-1983 (Box 7)
  - Dehnart, Jim 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    (Front-Line Report)
  - Donahue, Kathy 1995 (Box 7)
  - Donohoe, Elizabeth 1995 (Box 7)
    (The Little Red home School House home education supplies)
  - Farenga, Pat 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    (Growing Without Schooling)
  - Fessler, Diane 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    (Home Education Action Council)
  - Fitzhenry, Jack 1988-1989 (Box 7)
  - Friedl, Mary 1989 (Box 7)
  - Gaffney, Edward 1984 (Box 7)
    (re amicus brief filed on behalf of NCACS in the case of Aguilar v. Felton)
  - Garber, Les 1988 (Box 7)
    (Horizon School)
  - Gomez, Sandy 1983-1987 (Box 7)
  - Graber, Steven W. 1995 (Box 7)
    (Kansas attorney)
  - Green, Allene 1994 (Box 7)
  - Greenberg, Daniel 1989 (Box 7)
    (Sudbury Valley School)
  - Haas, Elsa 1990 (Box 7)
    (Madrid, Spain)
  - Hall, Sandi 1988-1991 (Box 7)
    (Washington Homeschool Organization)
  - Harris, Craig 1981 (Box 7)
    (Clonlara trustee)
  - Hart, Steven and Debbie 1984-1988 (Box 7)
  - Hassel, Mel 1985 (Box 7)
    (Alpha Omega, Tempe, AZ)
  - Hegener, Mark and Helen 1888-1991, 2 folders (Box 7)
    (Home Education Press, Tonasket, WA; include interview with Pat Montgomery)
  - Higgins, James J. 1984 (Box 7)
    (Liguorian Magazine)
  - Houk, Katharine 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    (Home Education Resource Service)
  - Hurley, Peig and Cormac 1983-2003 (Box 7)
  - Hurst, Sandy 1990-1992 (Box 7)
    (Upattinas School)
  - Johnson, Meg 1983 (Box 7)
  - Jones, Phil 1988 (Box 7)
  - Kaseman, Susan and M. Larry 1984-1985, 1990 (Box 7)
    (Wisconsin Parents' Association)
  - King, Cathy 1985 (Box 7)
  - Knowles, J. Gary 1989-1991 (Box 7)
  - Korn, Claire V. 1983-1991 (Box 7)
  - LaBeau, Janet 1984 (Box 7)
  - Lehman, Gene 1989 (Box 7)
    (LUNO; Learning Unlimited Network of Oregon)
  - Lines, Patricia M. (Box 7)
    (US Dept of Education, Office of Research working paper: Homeschooling: Private Choices and Public Obligations)
  - Lippitt, Ronald 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Loria, Olivia 1987-1991 (Box 7)
    (Pinewood School; NCACS)
  - Lundy, Marilyn F. 1984-1993 (Box 7)
    (Citizens for Educational Freedom)
  - McCurdy, Kathleen 1989-1991 (Box 7)
    (Family Learning Organization of Washington State; National Home School Association)
  - McIntyre, Lynne 1998-2000 (Box 7)
    (Nonpublic School Advisory Committee)
  - McMahon, Peggy O'Mara 1984 (Box 7)
    (Mothering Magazine)
  - Manahan, Larry 1989 (Box 7)
    (Ohio state legislator)
  - Mero, Paul T. 1994 (Box 7)
  - Mikelsons, Nancy and Don Goldhamer 1988 (Box 7)
  - Miller, Ron 1999-2000 (Box 7)
    (New Visions Foundation)
  - Mintz, Jerry 1985-1995, 2 folders (Box 7)
    (NCACS national coordinator)
  - Mohr, Joyce 1998-2000 (Box 7)
  - Moitozo, Steve 1991 (Box 7)
    (Homeschool Associates of New England)
  - Molnar, Steve 1983-1987 (Box 8)
    (Central America Peace Project)
  - Moore, Phil 1984 (Box 8)
    (Upland Hills Farms School)
  - Moore, Raymond and Dorothy 1981-1995, 2 folders (Box 8)
    (The Moore Foundation)
  - Mullarney, Maire 1982-1983 (Box 8)
    (The Mill House)
  - Nagel, Ed 1990-2001, 2 folders (Box 8)
    (National Association for the Legal Support of Alternative Schools; National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools)
  - Olson, Becky 1990 (Box 8)
    (National Homeschool Association)
  - O'Malley, Charles 1989-1991 (Box 8)
    (Executive Assistant for Private Education, US Dept. of Education)
  - Paul, Rob and Diane (New York home-schooling regulations) (Box 8)
  - Peavey, Sam B. 1988 (Box 8)
    (compulsory education study committee testimony, Des Moines, Iowa)
  - Pedro Albizu Campos Puerto Rican High School, Chicago 1987-1988, 3 folders (Box 8)
    (Ferd Eggan; Marvin Garcia)
  - Platt, Bill 1983-1984 (Box 8)
  - Pride, Mary 1989 (Box 8)
    (curriculum buyer's guide)
  - Puwal, Bernadine 1984 (Box 8)
    (letters from members of the Michigan Legislature)
  - Readhead, Zoe 1991 (Box 8)
    (Summerhill School)
  - Reed, Donn 1984, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Rothfeld, Mary 1989 (Box 8)
  - Sheffer, Susannah 1984-1990 (Box 8)
    (Holt Associates)
  - Sheldon, Gabriella and Ernest 1982-1983, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Shultis, Dan 1987-1990 (Box 8)
    (Peloncillo Primary, Rodelo NM, NHA; NCACS)
  - Simkus, Barbara 1994 (Box 8)
    (21st Century Education Resources)
  - Skenes, Robert 1988-1998 (Box 8)
    (National College of Education)
  - Smith, Dennis and Roxanne 1986-1993, 2 folders (Box 8)
    (Information Network for Christian Homes)
  - Staniloui, John 1989 (Box 8)
  - Stevens, Earl 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    (Talk About Learning, Portland, Maine)
  - Stevens, Janet 1986-1989 (Box 8)
  - Stich, Nancy 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    (Alaska Homeschool Association)
  - Vorys, Lucia 1983-1996 (Box 8)
  - Wartes, Jon 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    (public high school counselor and homeschool parent)
  - Werner, Dorothy 1989 (Box 8)
    (Illinois Home Education)
- Organization File
  The Organizational File series is composed of correspondence, publications, and other documents pertaining to alternative education organizations throughout the country. Time periods for these documents are noted in the file listing.
  - American Homeschool Association 1995 (Box 8)
  - Christian Home Educators of Michigan (CHEM) 1993 (Box 8)
  - Christian Home Educators of Ohio (CHEO) 1988-1990 (Box 8)
  - Citizens for Educational Freedom 1995 (Box 8)
  - Council for American Private Education (CAPE), Exemplary Private School Recognition Project 1983-1985, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Gentle Wind School (Surry, Maine) 1989 (Box 8)
  - Global Alliance for Transforming Education (GATE) 1991-1992 (Box 8)
  - Holt Associates 1988 (Box 8)
  - Home School Legal Defense Association 1987-1990 (Box 8)
  - International Alternative Schools Workshop and Conference 1995 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Alternative Education Organization 1995 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Association of Home Educators 1984 (Box 8)
  - National Association for the Legal Support of Alternative Schools (NALSAS) 1989-2001 (Box 8)
  - National Homeschool Association
    - 1988-1991 (Box 8)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 8)
  - Networking Organization for Independent Schools and Educators (NOISE) (Box 8)
  - Nonpublic School Advisory Committee 1994-1996, 2 folders (Box 8)
- National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools (NCACS) 1980-2001
  The series of the National Coalition of Alternative Community Schools contains the administrative records of the NCACS. Included are organizational bylaws, files from group conferences and retreats, correspondence of Patricia Montgomery as well as other members, proposals, instructional materials, articles, and member information. The time period for this series starts in 1980 and concludes with 2001.
  - Conference files (Box 9)
  - Board of Directors materials (Box 9)
  - By-laws of NCACS (Box 9)
  - Board meeting materials (Box 9)
  - 2000 Membership needs and assessment survey (Box 9)
  - Board manual (Box 9)
  - New participants (Box 9)
  - Article: "The Future is Now! A Profile of a National Organization," November 3, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Article: "Of Labels and Goals" (Box 9)
  - Directories, newsletters, etc. (Box 10)
- Home Schooling Background Material
  The Home Schooling Background Material series is several folders containing an assortment of source documents, primarily press clippings, which were used by Montgomery throughout her work.
  - Articles, etc. (Box 10)
- Clonlara Home Based Education Program
  The Clonlara Home Based Educational Program series documents the administrative and planning aspects of Clonlara's outreach training program. These materials, primarily conference information, correspondence, and brochures, date from the mid-1980s to roughly 1996.
  - Brochures and other materials, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Bethel Hawaii Conference 1993 (Box 11)
  - Conference evaluation forms 1987, 1994-1996, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Conference publications and organization (Box 11)
  - Mailings and correspondence (Box 11)
  - Publicity 1986 (Box 11)
  - Seminars: Michigan 1986 (Box 11)
  - Seminars: Canton, Toledo, Traverse City, and Lansing 1987 (Box 11)
  - Seminars: Flint, Detroit, Chicago, and Cleveland 1988 (Box 11)
  - West Coast Conference 1988 (Box 11)
- The Learning Edge
  The Learning Edge is the newsletter of the Home Based Education Program and Clonlara School. The series contains issues from April of 1984 to April of 2006. The researcher should be aware, however, that some months are missing issues.
  - April 1984-April 2006 (Box 12)
- Videocassettes
  The videocassettes include a number of instructional and promotional videos on the topic of alternative education.
  - H.R.6 debate recorded from C-SPAN 1994 (Box 12)
    (video no. 1)
  - Promotion video for Homebased Education Program (Box 12)
    (video no. 2)
  - "Maui Visions: The 1993 Trans-Pacific Conference on Educational Change" (Box 12)
    (video no. 3)
  - Talk on home education 1995 (Box 12)
    (video no. 4)
  - "Newsmaker," about CompuHigh (Box 12)
    (video no. 5)
- Audiocassettes
  The audiocassettes include speeches of, and interviews with, Montgomery. Other cassettes contain information about home schooling.
  - "The Difficult Child" (Box 12)
    (tape no. 1)
  - Recorded phone calls about a Pennsylvania family's court case (Box 12)
    (tape no. 2)
  - "Blueprints for Success," the Walkabout Program 1997 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 3)
  - "Clonlara in Japan," 1993 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 4)
  - "Clonlara School Secondary Program," 1997 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 5)
  - "Clonlara School Revised Curriculum," presenting new curriculum for grades 1-8 1997 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 6)
  - Home-schooling lecture, general description and philosophy 1994 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 7)
  - Montgomery at W.H.O. conference, "Home Education is a New Paradigm," 1994 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 8)
  - "Learning Disabilities: the Myth," education for special-needs children (Box 12)
    (tape no. 9)
  - "Home Education in Action," 1997 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 10)
  - "Relaxed Learning or Else," alternative approach to authoritarian control of education 1995 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 11)
  - "Making the Break: Leaving School and Getting a Life," 1996 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 12)
  - "The Home Schooling Decision," 1997 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 13)
  - Montgomery on WJR Detroit (Box 12)
    (tape no. 14)
  - Montgomery on WXYT (Box 12)
    (tape no. 15)
  - "Building Blocks of Learning," 1997 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 16)
  - Clonlara's Secondary Program, including Walkabout and CompuHigh 1996 (Box 12)
    (tape no. 17)